<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Λεωνίδας Λιάκος - Γεωγράφος. Leonidas Liakos - Geographer - Δημοσιεύσεις</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://geographer.gr/feeds/demosieuseis.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://geographer.gr/</id><updated>2022-12-14T10:20:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Challenges in the Geo-Processing of Big Soil Spatial Data</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/challenges-in-the-geo-processing-of-big-soil-spatial-data/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-14T10:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-12-14T10:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2022-12-14:/challenges-in-the-geo-processing-of-big-soil-spatial-data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Liakos, L.; Panagos, P. Challenges in the Geo-Processing of Big Soil
Spatial Data. Land 2022, 11, 2287. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/land11122287"&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/land11122287&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), IT-21027 Ispra,
Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study addressed a critical resource—soil—through the prism of
processing big data at the continental scale …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Liakos, L.; Panagos, P. Challenges in the Geo-Processing of Big Soil
Spatial Data. Land 2022, 11, 2287. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/land11122287"&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/land11122287&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), IT-21027 Ispra,
Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study addressed a critical resource—soil—through the prism of
processing big data at the continental scale. Rapid progress in
technology and remote sensing has majorly improved data processing on
extensive spatial and temporal scales. Here, the manuscript presents the
results of a systematic effort to geo-process and analyze soil-relevant
data. In addition, the main highlights include the difficulties
associated with using data infrastructures, managing big geospatial
data, decentralizing operations through remote access, mass processing,
and automating the data-processing workflow using advanced programming
languages. Challenges to this study included the reproducibility of the
results, their presentation in a communicative way, and the
harmonization of complex heterogeneous data in space and time based on
high standards of accuracy. Accuracy was especially important as the
results needed to be identical at all spatial scales (from point counts
to aggregated countrywide data). The geospatial modeling of soil
requires analysis at multiple spatial scales, from the pixel level,
through multiple territorial units (national or regional), and river
catchments, to the global scale. Advanced mapping methods (e.g., zonal
statistics, map algebra, choropleth maps, and proportional symbols) were
used to convey comprehensive and substantial information that would be
of use to policymakers. More specifically, a variety of cartographic
practices were employed, including vector and raster visualization and
hexagon grid maps at the global or European scale and in several
cartographic projections. The information was rendered in both grid
format and as aggregated statistics per polygon (zonal statistics),
combined with diagrams and an advanced graphical interface. The
uncertainty was estimated and the results were validated in order to
present the outputs in the most robust way. The study was also
interdisciplinary in nature, requiring large-scale datasets to be
integrated from different scientific domains, such as soil science,
geography, hydrology, chemistry, climate change, and agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="big data"></category><category term="data sharing"></category><category term="ESDAC"></category><category term="European soil observatory"></category><category term="soil policy"></category></entry><entry><title>European Soil Data Centre 2.0. Soil data and knowledge in support of the EU policies</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/european-soil-data-centre-2-0-soil-data-and-knowledge-in-support-of-the-eu-policies/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-14T10:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-12-14T10:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2022-12-14:/european-soil-data-centre-2-0-soil-data-and-knowledge-in-support-of-the-eu-policies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, P.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Van Liedekerke, M.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Borrelli,
P.&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;, Köninger, J.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Ballabio, C.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;,
Orgiazzi, A.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Lugato, E.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Liakos,
L.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Hervas, J.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Jones, A.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;,
Montanarella, L.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, 2022. European Soil Data Centre 2.0: Soil
data and knowledge in support of the EU …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, P.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Van Liedekerke, M.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Borrelli,
P.&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;, Köninger, J.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Ballabio, C.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;,
Orgiazzi, A.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Lugato, E.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Liakos,
L.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Hervas, J.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Jones, A.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;,
Montanarella, L.&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, 2022. European Soil Data Centre 2.0: Soil
data and knowledge in support of the EU policies. European J Soil
Science. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/ejss.13315"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/ejss.13315&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC),
Ispra, Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Department of Science, Roma Tre University, Rome,
Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Soil Data Centre (ESDAC), hosted by the European
Commission’s Joint Research Centre (JRC), is the focal point for soil
data, support to policy making and awareness raising for the European
Union (EU). Established in 2006 to provide harmonised soil-related
information for the EU Member States, and ESDAC currently hosts 88
datasets, 6000 maps, six atlases, 500 scientific publications, and a
copious amount of soil-related material. Through its data repository
publishing activity, ESDAC has licensed over 50,000 datasets during the
past 15 years; 8500 of them in 2021 alone. It has published 140 monthly
newsletters and is followed by more than 12,000 subscribed users, which
receive regular updates. This article addresses the use, usability, and
usefulness of ESDAC. About 75% of the ESDAC users come from academia and
the research community while the remaining 25% includes public
administration (at EU, national, regional, and local level) and the
private sector. In addition, we provide some insights of the datasets
evaluation and how they have been developed. The general ESDAC vision is
to provide evidence underlying EU soil-relevant policies and to
facilitate the access to relevant data for research. ESDAC is an
integral part of the recently established European Union Soil
Observatory (EUSO), with a target to have an even stronger role in
supporting EU and regional policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highlights&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ESDAC is a central place from where to find European wide relevant
soil data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ESDAC is an integral part of the EU Soil Observatory in creating
data and knowledge for policy support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ESDAC website shows a high volume of traffic; 10,000 of user
licenses are granted per year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ESDAC key success: open access data policy, documentation,
operational helpdesk and regular updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="(a) The trend in the ESDAC distributed datasets; (b) the cumulative number of released datasets. For 2022, an estimation is provided" src="https://geographer.gr/images/ejss13315-fig-0005-m.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;(a) The trend in the ESDAC distributed
datasets; (b) the cumulative number of released datasets. For 2022, an
estimation is provided&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="big data"></category><category term="data sharing"></category><category term="ESDAC"></category><category term="European soil observatory"></category><category term="soil policy"></category></entry><entry><title>Improving the phosphorus budget of European agricultural soils</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/improving-the-phosphorus-budget-of-european-agricultural-soils/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-17T10:20:00+03:00</published><updated>2022-09-17T10:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2022-09-17:/improving-the-phosphorus-budget-of-european-agricultural-soils/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, P.a, Köningner, J.a, Ballabio, C.a, Liakos, L.a, Muntwyler,
A.a, Borrelli, P.b , Lugato, E.a, 2022. Improving the phosphorus budget
of European agricultural soils. Science of The Total Environment 158706.
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158706&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a European Commission, Joint Research …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, P.a, Köningner, J.a, Ballabio, C.a, Liakos, L.a, Muntwyler,
A.a, Borrelli, P.b , Lugato, E.a, 2022. Improving the phosphorus budget
of European agricultural soils. Science of The Total Environment 158706.
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158706&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), Ispra, Italy b
Department of Science, Roma Tre University, Rome, Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite phosphorus (P) being crucial for plant nutrition and thus
food security, excessive P fertilization harms soil and aquatic
ecosystems. Accordingly, the European Green Deal and derived strategies
aim to reduce P losses and fertilizer consumption in agricultural soils.
The objective of this study is to calculate a soil P budget, allowing
the quantification of the P surpluses/deficits in the European Union
(EU) and the UK, considering the major inputs (inorganic fertilizers,
manure, atmospheric deposition, and chemical weathering) and outputs
(crop production, plant residues removal, losses by erosion) for the
period 2011–2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Land Use/Cover Area frame Survey (LUCAS) topsoil data include
measured values for almost 22,000 samples for both available and total
P. With advanced machine learning models, we developed maps for both
attributes at 500 m resolution. We estimated the available P for crops
at a mean value of 83 kg ha−1 with a clear distinction between North and
South. The ratio of available P to the total P is about 1:17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inorganic fertilizers and manure contribute almost equally as P
inputs (mean 16 ± 2 kg P ha−1 yr−1 at 90 % confidence level) to
agricultural soils, with high regional variations depending on farming
practices, livestock density, and cropping systems. The P outputs came
mainly from the exportation by the harvest of crop products and residues
(97.5 %) and, secondly, by erosion. Using a sediment distribution model,
we quantified the P fluxes to river basins and sea outlets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the EU and UK, we estimated an average surplus of 0.8 kg P ha−1
yr−1 with high variability between countries with some regional
variations. The P annual budget at regional scale showed ample
possibility to improve P management by both reducing inputs in regions
with high surplus (and P soil available) and rebalancing fertilization
in those at risk of soil fertility depletion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Phosphorus budget per each region as kg P ha−1. The vertical bars show the annual sum of P inputs (violet) and outputs (green) per country (expressed in tonnes)." src="https://geographer.gr/images/1-s2.0-S0048969722058053-gr9.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Phosphorus budget per each region as kg P
ha−1. The vertical bars show the annual sum of P inputs (violet) and
outputs (green) per country (expressed in tonnes).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="Agriculture"></category><category term="Farm to Fork"></category><category term="Fertilizers"></category><category term="Phosphorus budget"></category><category term="Plant uptake"></category></entry><entry><title>Global rainfall erosivity projections for 2050 and 2070</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/global-rainfall-erosivity-projections-for-2050-and-2070/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-11T10:20:00+03:00</published><updated>2022-05-11T10:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2022-05-11:/global-rainfall-erosivity-projections-for-2050-and-2070/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, P.a, Borrelli, P.b, Matthews, F.a, Liakos, L.a, Bezak, N.c,
Diodato, N.d, Ballabio, C.a, 2022. Global rainfall erosivity projections
for 2050 and 2070. Journal of Hydrology 610, 127865. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2022.127865"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2022.127865&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aEuropean Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, P.a, Borrelli, P.b, Matthews, F.a, Liakos, L.a, Bezak, N.c,
Diodato, N.d, Ballabio, C.a, 2022. Global rainfall erosivity projections
for 2050 and 2070. Journal of Hydrology 610, 127865. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2022.127865"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2022.127865&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aEuropean Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), Ispra, Italy
bDepartment of Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of Pavia,
27100 Pavia, Italy cUniversity of Ljubljana, Faculty of Civil and
Geodetic Engineering, Ljubljana, Slovenia dMet European Research
Observatory – International Affiliates Program of the University
Corporation for Atmospheric Research, Benevento, Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The erosive force of rainfall (rainfall erosivity) is a major driver
of soil, nutrient losses worldwide and an important input for soil
erosion assessments models. Here, we present a comprehensive set of
future erosivity projections at a 30 arc-second (∼1 km2) spatial scale
using 19 downscaled General Circulation Models (GCMs) simulating three
Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) for the periods 2041–2060
and 2061–2080. The future rainfall erosivity projections were obtained
based on a Gaussian Process Regression (GPR) approach relating rainfall
depth to rainfall erosivity through a series of (bio)climatic
covariates. Compared to the 2010 Global Rainfall erosivity baseline, we
estimate a potential average increase in global rainfall erosivity
between 26.2 and 28.8% for 2050 and 27–34.3% for 2070. Therefore,
climate change and the consequential increase in rainfall erosivity is
the main driver of the projected + 30–66% increase in soil erosion rates
by 2070.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results were successfully compared with 20 regional studies
addressing the rainfall erosivity projections. We release the whole
dataset of future rainfall erosivity projections composed of 102
simulation scenarios, with the aim to support further research
activities on soil erosion, soil conservation and climate change
communities. We expect these datasets to address the needs of both the
Earth system modeling community and policy makers. In addition, we
introduce a modeling approach to estimate future erosivity and make
further assessments at global and continental scales.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="Agriculture"></category><category term="Climate change"></category><category term="Food security"></category><category term="Land use change"></category><category term="Policy"></category><category term="R-factor"></category><category term="Soil health"></category></entry><entry><title>Exploring the possible role of satellite-based rainfall data in estimating inter- and intra-annual global rainfall erosivity</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/exploring-the-possible-role-of-satellite-based-rainfall-data-in-estimating-inter-and-intra-annual-global-rainfall-erosivity/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-04-14T10:20:00+03:00</published><updated>2022-04-14T10:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2022-04-14:/exploring-the-possible-role-of-satellite-based-rainfall-data-in-estimating-inter-and-intra-annual-global-rainfall-erosivity/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bezak, N., Borrelli, P., Panagos, P., 2022. Exploring the possible
role of satellite-based rainfall data in estimating inter- and
intra-annual global rainfall erosivity. Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci. 26,
1907–1924. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-26-1907-2022"&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-26-1907-2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Civil and Geodetic Engineering,
Ljubljana, Slovenia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2Department of Earth …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bezak, N., Borrelli, P., Panagos, P., 2022. Exploring the possible
role of satellite-based rainfall data in estimating inter- and
intra-annual global rainfall erosivity. Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci. 26,
1907–1924. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-26-1907-2022"&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-26-1907-2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Civil and Geodetic Engineering,
Ljubljana, Slovenia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of Pavia,
Pavia, Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3Department of Biological Environment, Kangwon National University,
Chuncheon 24341, Republic of Korea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), Ispra, Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite recent developments in modeling global soil erosion by water,
to date, no substantial progress has been made towards more dynamic
inter- and intra-annual assessments. In this regard, the main challenge
is still represented by the limited availability of high temporal
resolution rainfall data needed to estimate rainfall erosivity. As the
availability of high temporal resolution rainfall data will most likely
not increase in future decades since the monitoring networks have been
declining since the 1980s, the suitability of alternative approaches to
estimate global rainfall erosivity using satellite-based rainfall data
was explored in this study. For this purpose, we used the high spatial
and temporal resolution global precipitation estimates obtained with the
National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) Climate Data
Record (CDR) Climate Prediction Center MORPHing (CMORPH) technique. Such
high spatial and temporal (30 min) resolution data have not yet been
used for the estimation of rainfall erosivity on a global scale.
Alternatively, the erosivity density (ED) concept was also used to
estimate global rainfall erosivity. The obtained global estimates of
rainfall erosivity were validated against the pluviograph data included
in the Global Rainfall Erosivity Database (GloREDa). Overall, results
indicated that the CMORPH estimates have a marked tendency to
underestimate rainfall erosivity when compared to the GloREDa estimates.
The most substantial underestimations were observed in areas with the
highest rainfall erosivity values. At the continental level, the best
agreement between annual CMORPH and interpolated GloREDa rainfall
erosivity maps was observed in Europe, while the worst agreement was
detected in Africa and South America. Further analyses conducted at the
monthly scale for Europe revealed seasonal misalignments, with the
occurrence of underestimation of the CMORPH estimates in the summer
period and overestimation in the winter period compared to GloREDa. The
best agreement between the two approaches to estimate rainfall erosivity
was found for fall, especially in central and eastern Europe. Conducted
analysis suggested that satellite-based approaches for estimation of
rainfall erosivity appear to be more suitable for low-erosivity regions,
while in high-erosivity regions (&amp;gt; 1000–2000 MJ mm ha−1 h−1 yr−1) and
seasons (&amp;gt; 150–250 MJ mm ha−1 h−1 month−1), the agreement with
estimates obtained from pluviographs (GloREDa) is lower. Concerning the
ED estimates, this second approach to estimate rainfall erosivity
yielded better agreement with GloREDa estimates compared to CMORPH,
which could be regarded as an expected result since this approach
indirectly uses the GloREDa data. The application of a simple-linear
function correction of the CMORPH data was applied to provide a better
fit to GloREDa and correct systematic underestimation. This correction
improved the performance of CMORPH, but in areas with the highest
rainfall erosivity rates, the underestimation was still observed. A
preliminary trend analysis of the CMORPH rainfall erosivity estimates
was also performed for the 1998–2019 period to investigate possible
changes in the rainfall erosivity at a global scale, which has not yet
been conducted using high-frequency data such as CMORPH. According to
this trend analysis, an increasing and statistically significant trend
was more frequently observed than a decreasing trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mean global rainfall erosivity map for the 1998–2019 period based on the CMORPH product (a) and ED concept using ERA5 (b)." src="https://geographer.gr/images/hess-26-1907-2022-f02-web-1536x471.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Mean global rainfall erosivity map for
the 1998–2019 period based on the CMORPH product (a) and ED concept
using ERA5 (b).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="rainfall"></category><category term="erosivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Phosphorus plant removal from European agricultural land</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/phosphorus-plant-removal-from-european-agricultural-land/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-07T10:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-02-07T10:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2022-02-07:/phosphorus-plant-removal-from-european-agricultural-land/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, Panos&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Anna Muntwyler&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Leonidas
Liakos&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Pasquale Borrelli&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;, Irene
Biavetti&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Mariia Bogonos&lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt; , and Emanuele
Lugato&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;. 2022. “Phosphorus Plant Removal from European
Agricultural Land.” Journal of Consumer Protection and Food Safety,
February. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00003-022-01363-3"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00003-022-01363-3&lt;/a&gt;.^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; European Commission, Joint Research Centre …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panagos, Panos&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Anna Muntwyler&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Leonidas
Liakos&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Pasquale Borrelli&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;, Irene
Biavetti&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Mariia Bogonos&lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt; , and Emanuele
Lugato&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;. 2022. “Phosphorus Plant Removal from European
Agricultural Land.” Journal of Consumer Protection and Food Safety,
February. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00003-022-01363-3"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00003-022-01363-3&lt;/a&gt;.^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), Ispra,
Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt; Dipartimento di Scienze della Terra e dell’Ambiente,
Università degli Studi di Pavia, Pavia, Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt; European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC),
Seville, Spain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phosphorus (P) is an important nutrient for all plant growth and it
has become a critical and often imbalanced element in modern
agriculture. A proper crop fertilization is crucial for production,
farmer profits, and also for ensuring sustainable agriculture. The
European Commission has published the Farm to Fork (F2F) Strategy in May
2020, in which the reduction of the use of fertilizers by at least 20%
is among one of the main objectives. Therefore, it is important to look
for the optimal use of P in order to reduce its pollution effects but
also ensure future agricultural production and food security. It is
essential to estimate the P budget with the best available data at the
highest possible spatial resolution. In this study, we focused on
estimating the P removal from soils by crop harvest and removal of crop
residues. Specifically, we attempted to estimate the P removal by taking
into account the production area and productivity rates of 37 crops for
220 regions in the European Union (EU) and the UK. To estimate the P
removal by crops, we included the P concentrations in plant tissues (%),
the crop humidity rates, the crop residues production, and the removal
rates of the crop residues. The total P removal was about 2.55 million
tonnes (Mt) (± 0.23 Mt), with crop harvesting having the larger
contribution (ca. 94%) compared to the crop residues removal. A
Monte-Carlo analysis estimated a ± 9% uncertainty. In addition, we
performed a projection of P removal from agricultural fields in 2030. By
providing this picture, we aim to improve the current P balances in the
EU and explore the feasibility of F2F objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Total phosphorus removal per country and region. Green bars aggregate P crop removal per country and brown ones are the aggregated P removal with residues." src="https://geographer.gr/images/3_2022_1363_Fig7_HTML.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Total phosphorus removal per country and
region. Green bars aggregate P crop removal per country and brown ones
are the aggregated P removal with residues.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="Crop production"></category><category term="Farm to Fork"></category><category term="Food security"></category><category term="Nutrients"></category><category term="Phosphorus budget"></category><category term="Phosphorus removal"></category><category term="Plant uptake"></category></entry><entry><title>Μοντέλα αστικής εξάπλωσης και παρακολούθηση με τηλεπισκόπηση νυκτερινών φώτων.</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/montela-astikes-exaploses-kai-parakolouthese-me-telepiskopese-nukterinon-photon/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-24T10:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-11-24T10:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2021-11-24:/montela-astikes-exaploses-kai-parakolouthese-me-telepiskopese-nukterinon-photon/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Στα πλαίσια της δημοσιοποίησης των αποτελεσμάτων της διδακτορικής μου
διατριβής με θέμα &lt;strong&gt;“Μοντέλα αστικής εξάπλωσης και παρακολούθηση
με τηλεπισκόπηση νυκτερινών φώτων”&lt;/strong&gt; έχει αναρτηθεί ειδική
ενότητα στην διεύθυνση &lt;a class="uri" href="https://phd.geographer.gr/"&gt;https://phd.geographer.gr/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Η διατριβή είναι διαθέσιμη στο &lt;a href="https://www.didaktorika.gr/eadd/handle/10442/50223"&gt;Εθνικό Αρχείο
Διδακτορικών Διατριβών&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Η διατριβή στοχεύει στην παρακολούθηση και ανάλυση της λειτουργίας
των …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Στα πλαίσια της δημοσιοποίησης των αποτελεσμάτων της διδακτορικής μου
διατριβής με θέμα &lt;strong&gt;“Μοντέλα αστικής εξάπλωσης και παρακολούθηση
με τηλεπισκόπηση νυκτερινών φώτων”&lt;/strong&gt; έχει αναρτηθεί ειδική
ενότητα στην διεύθυνση &lt;a class="uri" href="https://phd.geographer.gr/"&gt;https://phd.geographer.gr/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Η διατριβή είναι διαθέσιμη στο &lt;a href="https://www.didaktorika.gr/eadd/handle/10442/50223"&gt;Εθνικό Αρχείο
Διδακτορικών Διατριβών&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Η διατριβή στοχεύει στην παρακολούθηση και ανάλυση της λειτουργίας
των ελληνικών αστικών περιοχών μέσω της εκμετάλλευσης μιας ιδιαίτερης
κατηγορίας δεδομένων τηλεπισκόπησης, των νυκτερινών φώτων. Τα νυκτερινά
φώτα έχει παρατηρηθεί ότι αντικατοπτρίζουν σε σημαντικό βαθμό τα επίπεδα
αστικής και οικονομικής ανάπτυξης και είναι άρρηκτα συνδεδεμένα με
οικονομικά μεγέθη όπως το ΑΕΠ, ο πληθυσμός, η οικοδομική δραστηριότητα
και η κατανάλωση του ηλεκτρικού ρεύματος.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Η διεξαγωγή της διατριβής υποστηρίζεται από τα κυριότερα σύνολα
δεδομένων νυκτερινών φώτων (DMPS/OLS, snpp-VIIRS, ISS) για την αποτύπωση
της ελληνικής αστικής «πραγματικότητας». Τα δεδομένα νυχτερινών φώτων
διατίθενται χωρίς να έχουν υποστεί την απαραίτητη προεπεξεργασία για την
αφαίρεση παραγόντων που επηρεάζουν την ποιότητά τους και τα
αποτελέσματατης έρευνας. Σημαντικοί εξωγενείς παράγοντες επιρροής της
ποιότητας των δεδομένων, όπως η σεληνιακή ακτινοβολία, δεν έχουν
αφαιρεθεί. Τεχνικά χαρακτηριστικά και περιορισμοί όπως η υπερλάμψη και ο
κορεσμός των δεδομένων DSMP/OLS συνεχίζουν να απασχολούν την
επιστημονική κοινότητα.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Στα πλαίσια της διατριβής θα προταθούν μεθόδοι για την διόρθωση της
σεληνιακής ακτινοβολίας από τα δεδομένα snpp-VIIRS και θα επιχειρηθεί η
βελτίωση των δεδομένων DMSP/OLS με την συνδρομή δεδομένων SAR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Στόχος της διατριβής είναι να εκμεταλλευτεί τα δεδομένα νυχτερινών
φώτων για να καταγράψει την εποχικότητα των αστικών περιοχών στον
Ελλαδικό χώρο, να προσομοιώσει την αστική διάχυση που θα λάβει χώρα στο
μέλλον, να προβλέψει την ένταση της αστικής δραστηριότητας, να εκτιμήσει
σε λεπτομερή χωρική και χρονική κλίμακα οικονομικές μεταβλητές όπως το
ΑΕΠ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Τα νυχτερινά φώτα θα χρησιμοποιηθούν για να αποτιμηθούν οι συνέπειες
έκτακτων συνθηκών στην αστική δραστηριότητα, για να εκτιμηθεί η
επιβάρυνση από την φωτορύπανση και για να περιγραφούν τα πρότυπα
μετακίνησης στις σύγχρονες ελληνικές πόλεις.Από τα αποτελέσματα
προκύπτουν αξιόλογες και καινοτόμες μέθοδοι για την βελτίωση των
δεδομένων και την ανάλυση, πρόβλεψη και ερμηνεία των αστικών φαινομένων.
Η χρήση νυχτερινών φώτων αποτελεί ένα σημαντικό εργαλείο στα χέρια του
ερευνητή αλλά απαιτεί βαθειά επίγνωση των τεχνικών περιορισμών και των
εξωγενών παράγοντων που επηρεάζουν τις δυνατότητές τους.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="night time lights"></category><category term="phd"></category></entry><entry><title>Mercury in European topsoils. Anthropogenic sources, stocks and fluxes</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/mercury-in-european-topsoils-anthropogenic-sources-stocks-and-fluxes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-16T10:20:00+03:00</published><updated>2021-07-16T10:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2021-07-16:/mercury-in-european-topsoils-anthropogenic-sources-stocks-and-fluxes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panos Panagosa, Martin Jiskrab, Pasquale Borrellic, Leonidas Liakosa,
Cristiano Ballabioa. 2021. “Mercury in European Topsoils: Anthropogenic
Sources, Stocks and Fluxes.” Environmental Research, June, 111556. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2021.111556"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2021.111556&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), Ispra, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental Geosciences, University of Basel, Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Department of Earth …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Panos Panagosa, Martin Jiskrab, Pasquale Borrellic, Leonidas Liakosa,
Cristiano Ballabioa. 2021. “Mercury in European Topsoils: Anthropogenic
Sources, Stocks and Fluxes.” Environmental Research, June, 111556. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2021.111556"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2021.111556&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), Ispra, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental Geosciences, University of Basel, Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of Pavia,
27100, Pavia, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mercury (Hg) is one of the most dangerous pollutants worldwide. In
the European Union (EU), we recently estimated the Hg distribution in
topsoil using 21,591 samples and a series of geo-physical inputs. In
this manuscript, we investigate the impact of mining activities,
chrol-alkali industries and other diffuse pollution sources as primary
anthropogenic sources of Hg hotspots in the EU. Based on Hg measured
soil samples, we modelled the Hg pool in EU topsoils, which totals about
44.8 Gg, with an average density of 103 g ha−1. As a following step, we
coupled the estimated Hg stocks in topsoil with the pan-European
assessment of soil loss due to water erosion and sediment distribution.
In the European Union and UK, we estimated that about 43 Mg Hg yr−1 are
displaced by water erosion and c. a. 6 Mg Hg yr−1 are transferred with
sediments to river basins and eventually released to coastal Oceans. The
Mediterranean Sea receives almost half (2.94 Mg yr−1) of the Hg fluxes
to coastal oceans and it records the highest quantity of Hg sediments.
This is the result of elevated soil Hg concentration and high erosion
rates in the catchments draining into the Mediterranean Sea. This work
contributes to new knowledge in support of the policy development in the
EU on the Zero Pollution Action Plan and the Sustainable Development
Goal (SDGs) 3.9 and 14.1, which both have as an objective to reduce soil
pollution by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to Dataset: &lt;a href="https://esdac.jrc.ec.europa.eu/content/mercury-content-european-union-topsoil"&gt;Mercury
content in the European Union topsoil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Map of Hg stock (g ha−1) in European topsoils." src="https://geographer.gr/images/1-s2.0-S0013935121008501-gr4.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Map of Hg stock (g ha−1) in European
topsoils.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Estimated Hg losses to river basins and Hg fluxes to sea outlets (Mg yr−1) due to water erosion." src="https://geographer.gr/images/1-s2.0-S0013935121008501-gr8.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Estimated Hg losses to river basins and
Hg fluxes to sea outlets (Mg yr−1) due to water erosion.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Estimated Hg displaced with water erosion per catchment. The vertical bars show the annual Hg eroded (green) and deposited (orange) per country." src="https://geographer.gr/images/1-s2.0-S0013935121008501-gr6.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Estimated Hg displaced with water erosion
per catchment. The vertical bars show the annual Hg eroded (green) and
deposited (orange) per country.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="Heavy metal"></category><category term="Hg"></category><category term="Sediment transport"></category><category term="Soil contamination"></category><category term="Soil erosion"></category></entry><entry><title>An in-depth statistical analysis of the rainstorms erosivity in Europe</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/an-in-depth-statistical-analysis-of-the-rainstorms-erosivity-in-europe/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-15T10:20:00+03:00</published><updated>2021-07-15T10:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2021-07-15:/an-in-depth-statistical-analysis-of-the-rainstorms-erosivity-in-europe/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nejc Bezaka, Matjaž Mikoša, Pasquale Borrellibc, Leonidas Liakosd,
Panos Panagosd. 2021. “An In-Depth Statistical Analysis of the
Rainstorms Erosivity in Europe.” CATENA 206 (November): 105577. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2021.105577"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2021.105577&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a .University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Civil and Geodetic
Engineering, Slovenia b. Department of Earth and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nejc Bezaka, Matjaž Mikoša, Pasquale Borrellibc, Leonidas Liakosd,
Panos Panagosd. 2021. “An In-Depth Statistical Analysis of the
Rainstorms Erosivity in Europe.” CATENA 206 (November): 105577. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2021.105577"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2021.105577&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a .University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Civil and Geodetic
Engineering, Slovenia b. Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences,
University of Pavia, Italy c. Department of Biological Environment,
Kangwon National University, Chuncheon 24341, Republic of Korea
d. European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC), Ispra, Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heavy rainstorms play a central role in the water-driving soil
erosion processes. An in-depth knowledge about temporal and spatial
erosivity of rainfall events is required to gain a better understanding
of soil erosion processes and optimize soil protection measures
efficiency. In this study, the spatiotemporal distribution of more than
300,000 erosive events measured at 1181 locations, part of the Rainfall
Erosivity Database at European Scale (REDES) database, is studied to
shed some new light on the rainfall erosivity in Europe. Rainfall
erosive events are statistically investigated through the Lorenz curve
and derived coefficients such as the Gini coefficient (G). Additionally,
seasonal characteristics of the most and the less erosive events are
compared to investigate seasonal characteristics of rainstorms across
Europe. The G shows largest values of inequality of the inter-annual
temporal distribution of the rainfall erosive events in the Alpine
region, mostly due to the large number of rainfall events with smaller
rainfall erosivity. While for other parts of Europe, the inequality
described by the G is mostly due to a small number of high erosive
events. The G slightly decreases from south to north while no clear
regional patterns can be detected. Additionally, in Europe, on average
11% (ranging from 1 to 24%) of all erosive events contribute to form 50%
of the total rainfall erosivity. Furthermore, higher erosive rainfall
events tend to occur later in the year compared to less erosive events
that take place earlier. To our knowledge, this study is the first one
addressing event scale rainfall erosivity distribution using more than
300,000 rainfall erosivity events and covering almost a whole continent.
Scientifically our findings represent a major step towards large-scale
process-based erosion modelling while, practically, they provide new
elements that can support national and local soil erosion monitoring
programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Percentage of rainfall erosive events by number that contribute to the 50% of the total erosivity (D50). Rainfall erosivity map of Europe is shown as background (Panagos et al., 2015a)." src="https://geographer.gr/images/1-s2.0-S0341816221004355-gr7.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Percentage of rainfall erosive events by
number that contribute to the 50% of the total erosivity (D50). Rainfall
erosivity map of Europe is shown as background (Panagos et al.,
2015a).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Gini coefficients (G) for the 1181 stations across Europe using all rainfall erosive events included in the REDES database. As a background map, the six K-means clusters as defined by Ballabio et al. (2017) are shown." src="https://geographer.gr/images/1-s2.0-S0341816221004355-gr2.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Gini coefficients (G) for the 1181
stations across Europe using all rainfall erosive events included in the
REDES database. As a background map, the six K-means clusters as defined
by Ballabio et al. (2017) are shown.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="Rainfall erosivity"></category><category term="REDES"></category><category term="Lorenz curve"></category><category term="Gini coefficient"></category><category term="Seasonality"></category><category term="Threshold values"></category><category term="R-factor"></category><category term="Europe"></category></entry><entry><title>Median Shift Lunar Correction for VIIRS</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/median-shift-lunar-correction-for-viirs/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-06-08T10:30:00+03:00</published><updated>2021-06-08T10:30:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2021-06-08:/median-shift-lunar-correction-for-viirs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Stathakis, Demetris&lt;em&gt;, and Leonidas Liakos&lt;/em&gt;. 2020. “Median
Shift Lunar Correction for VIIRS.” IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing
Letters, 1–5. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1109/LGRS.2020.3007965"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1109/LGRS.2020.3007965&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Thessaly, Spatial Analysis/GIS and Thematic Mapping
Laboratory, Department of Planning and Regional Development, Sekeri
&amp;amp; Alamanas, Volos, Greece&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visible Infrared …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Stathakis, Demetris&lt;em&gt;, and Leonidas Liakos&lt;/em&gt;. 2020. “Median
Shift Lunar Correction for VIIRS.” IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing
Letters, 1–5. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1109/LGRS.2020.3007965"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1109/LGRS.2020.3007965&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Thessaly, Spatial Analysis/GIS and Thematic Mapping
Laboratory, Department of Planning and Regional Development, Sekeri
&amp;amp; Alamanas, Volos, Greece&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visible Infrared Imaging Radiometer Suite (VIIRS) 24-h data are
substantially affected by lunar illumination. A new method is proposed
to correct this distortion and be able to form a consistent time series.
The method has the advantage of being relatively simple in its
deployment while at the same time effective. The results show that the
proposed method removes periodical illumination noise due to the lunar
circle while preserving meaningful information, in the test sites
applied.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="Night time lights"></category><category term="DMSP/OLS"></category><category term="VIIRS"></category><category term="Lunar Correction"></category></entry><entry><title>Further adjustment of the Defense Meteorological Satellite Program-Operational Linescan System using radar data</title><link href="https://geographer.gr/further-adjustment-of-the-defense-meteorological-satellite-program-operational-linescan-system-using-radar-data/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-06-08T10:20:00+03:00</published><updated>2021-06-08T10:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Leonidas Liakos</name></author><id>tag:geographer.gr,2021-06-08:/further-adjustment-of-the-defense-meteorological-satellite-program-operational-linescan-system-using-radar-data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Stathakis, Demetris, and Leonidas Liakos. 2019. “Further Adjustment
of the Defense Meteorological Satellite Program-Operational Linescan
System Using Radar Data.” Journal of Applied Remote Sensing 13 (03):
034507/1-9. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1117/1.JRS.13.034507"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1117/1.JRS.13.034507&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Thessaly, Spatial Analysis/GIS and Thematic Mapping
Laboratory, Department of Planning …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Stathakis, Demetris, and Leonidas Liakos. 2019. “Further Adjustment
of the Defense Meteorological Satellite Program-Operational Linescan
System Using Radar Data.” Journal of Applied Remote Sensing 13 (03):
034507/1-9. &lt;a class="uri" href="https://doi.org/10.1117/1.JRS.13.034507"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1117/1.JRS.13.034507&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Thessaly, Spatial Analysis/GIS and Thematic Mapping
Laboratory, Department of Planning and Regional Development, Sekeri
&amp;amp; Alamanas, Volos, Greece&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the Defense Meteorological Satellite Program—Operational
Linescan System (DSMP/OLS) data have been successfully adjusted based on
the presence of vegetation in each pixel. We propose a further
adjustment based on radar data obtained by the SeaWinds scatterometer.
It is shown that the adjustment results in substantial accuracy gains,
measured as increased correlation with the more accurate Visible
Infrared Imaging Radiometer Suite data as well as with the existing
instances of radiance calibrated DSMP/OLS data. The proposed adjust-
ment is easy to implement. The improvement of the proposed method is
particularly significant in arid regions where vegetation is relatively
sparse.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Δημοσιεύσεις"></category><category term="Night time lights"></category><category term="DMSP/OLS"></category><category term="SAR"></category></entry></feed>